A Guide to the Doug Burton Papers, 1962, 1977-1979
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Doug Burton Papers, 1962, 1977-1979 [bulk 1978-1979]
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2020-001
Much of this collection has been digitized and is available online.
1.17 Cubic Feet; 1 box
This collection contains Doug Burton's papers and memorabilia from a Pratt-funded Virginia Tech engineering trip to the USSR and Finland taken in March 1979. It primarily consists of VT trip handouts, maps, a newspaper, Moscow Olympics souvenirs, some books, and a transcript of Doug Burton's diary.
Burton, Thomas Douglas
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Doug Burton Papers was donated to Special Collections in 2016.
Alternate Form Available
Much of this collection has been digitized and is available online.
Biographical Note
Thomas Douglas (Doug) Burton graduated from Virginia Tech in 1980 with a B.S. in electrical engineering. While a student, Burton was one of about 30 students and professors to visit the USSR and Finland in the Spring of 1979 as part of a study abroad trip for the Virginia Tech College of Engineering. Following graduation, Burton joined Bell Telephone Labs and earned a master's at Cal Tech. He later worked for GE, Otis Elevators, and other companies, before returning to Blacksburg, Virginia, to join Luna Technologies and Luna Innovations in 2001. He retired in January 2019.
Administrative History
John Lee Pratt (an industrialist who provided financial support for Virginia Tech as early as 1957) died in 1975, leaving in his will approximately $12 million for Virginia Tech, half to be used to support programs within the College of Engineering. In his will, Pratt specified that the funds had to be put towards the support of research and scholarships. It was decided that the Pratt funds were going to be put towards four distinct programs: one half towards a scholarship program, one fourth towards a graduate fellowship program, one eighth used for the funding of international travel for facility, and the remaining one eighth for a study abroad program for undergraduate students. One of those study abroad trips was one taken from March 16 to March 30 in 1979 to the USSR, and documented in Doug Burton's diary, as seen in this collection.
Scope and Content
This collection contains trip handouts, three books, the Pratt report of the trip, Moscow Olympics souvenirs, "The Truth" Russian newspaper, brochures and maps, a hotel card, "Love an Engineer" button, a Russian receipt, and digital copies of photos, letters, and Doug Burton's diary.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by type.
Index Terms
Subjects:
University Archives; University History
Organizations:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. College of Engineering (1964-)
People:
Burton, Thomas Douglas
Contents List
Much of this collection has been digitized and is available online.
- Trip Correspondence and Summary, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Russia Trip Guidelines, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Excerpts from Doug Burton's Diary (Pratt Report), 1979-03-16-1979-03-30, 1979-06-07 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Hotel Card, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Russian Receipt, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Russian Newspaper, 1979-03-27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Trip Maps, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Digital Copies of the Trip's Photos, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Love an Engineer" Button, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Next Time You go to Russia" Guidebook, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Russian Dictionary, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "The Russians" by Hedrick Smith, 1976 (Box 1)
- Moscow Olympics Souvenirs, undated (Box 1)